<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/www/www.gentoo.org/raw_cvs/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/handbook/hb-introduction.xml,v 1.2 2004/07/18 09:30:26 plasmaroo Exp $ -->

<sections>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The aim of this handbook is to outline Gentoo development policies, and make
<e>you</e>, the developer, informed of policies, standards and procedures which
Gentoo considers to be core values of our development system.
</p>

<p>
This handbook is not intended to be the universal guide to everything
- the opportunities open to you are endless, and as a result, this
handbook is designed to teach you the principles which we think make
up a good Gentoo developer - the rest is up to you!
</p>

<p>
If you are new to Gentoo development or even an old veteran and are at
any stage unsure about anything, feel free to ask the gentoo-dev
mailing list, or #gentoo-dev.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Requirements</title>
<body>
<p>
Before you start to tinker, it is important to have a working Gentoo
installation, both for documentation and development purposes, and we
also recommend that you have a good knowledge of topics covered in the
``Working with Gentoo'' section in the User Handbook to help you with
your development work.
</p>
<p>
Most of this guide is targeted at developers, but, if you are just
interested to see what makes Gentoo development work, this guide may
provide some valuable insights.
</p>
<p>
The best way to get noticed [ and to possibly become a Gentoo
developer! ] is to file intuitive and accurate bug reports at the <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugzilla</uri>, with patches if
possible, and to help us out with what you think would make a better
Gentoo for everyone whether by providing patches for new features, 
submitting new ebuilds, or solving issues with existing ones.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</sections>
