<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/www/www.gentoo.org/raw_cvs/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/handbook/hb-introduction-whatyouget.xml,v 1.3 2004/07/20 08:54:34 plasmaroo Exp $ -->

<sections>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo provides developers with all the necessary services which they
might need for their development efforts. If you require anything
else, please do not hesitate to contact the Infrastructure Team!
</p>

<p>
Once you are an authorized developer, your recruiter should organize
the following services.  If you experience any problems, please see
your recruiter or the mentioned staff with access to the required
service.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<body>

<p>
Developers are able to change all aspects of bugs in Bugzilla. If you
have an existing account the email address should be changed to your
Gentoo address by a Bugzilla administrator.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CVS</title>
<body>

<p>
Not all developers receive CVS access - if you require Portage access
to the gentoo, gentoo-projects, or gentoo-x86 tree get someone on the
recruiters team to do this for you. You may need to justify your need
for this to happen, however.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>IRC</title>
<body>

<p>
When you are a developer, you will receive operator status on
#gentoo-dev signifying that you are a developer. Please contact
Developer Relations if you do not. Additionally, team leads may decide
to give you operator status on specialized channels such as
#gentoo-hardened, for example. Abuse of operator powers on #gentoo-dev
may lead to your operator powers being removed instantly along with
the possible removal of your developership. If you are given operator powers,
we ask that you use them constructively to benefit everybody when either
developers or users break up the cleanliness of the channels.
</p>

<p>
Operator status on #gentoo is given at discretion by Developer
Relations; it does not in any way signify that the user is a developer.
</p>

<p>
"Special" Gentoo channels such as #gentoo-hardened and #gentoo-server are
given to people at the discretion of the team - in this case, the hardened
and server teams.
</p>

<p>
IRC Channels are owned by their relevant project leads, whether strategical
or operational and the owner has the discretion of voicing or unvoicing
members of the public. If you believe that those powers are being abused or
are being used with wrong considerations; then speak to the Gentoo Linux
Developer Relations team, or the Ombudsman.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Forums [Optional]</title>
<body>

<p>
Ask one of the forums administrators to update your forum status on
the Gentoo Forums, if needed. Forum accounts are not mandatory.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mail</title>
<body>

<p>
All developers are provided with a developer@gentoo.org mail address
for Gentoo use.
</p>

<p>
Please see <uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/dev-email.xml</uri> 
for more details.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mailing lists</title>
<body>

<p>
All developers should be subscribed on the gentoo-core and gentoo-dev mailing
lists. Contact the someone on the recruiters team to subscribe you to
the gentoo-core developer-only mailing list or if you have any
trouble.  If you are subscribed on any other Gentoo mailing lists, you
should unsubscribe and resubscribe with your new mail address.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Shell access</title>
<body>

<p>
Developers currently get a shell account on dev.gentoo.org (
toucan.gentoo.org ) - this provides mail storage, SMTP relaying and also
an IRC tunnel for developers to use to access freenode.
</p>

<p>
To ensure security, access is only available through SSH keys, which
your mentor should place on your account and allow you to log in:
please see <uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/cvs-sshkeys.xml</uri>
for more details regarding SSH keys..
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Service usage policies</title>
<body>
<p>
Services provided by Gentoo should only be used for Gentoo development
work. Infrastructure has the right to disable any accounts which are a
security risk, these include inactive accounts which will be
suspended by the infrastructure team if you are presumed idle, 
and your IRC #gentoo-dev status would also be voiced.
</p>
<p>
If any files in your account are found to be harmful towards other developers
or users on the box, or pose a risk to the Gentoo project (such as illegal
.torrents), Gentoo Infrastructure will suspend your account which would only
be unlocked after investigation from Gentoo Developer Relations. In most cases,
your developership may be suspended if such files are found. The same
policies also apply to Gentoo CVS and other Gentoo-provided services you may
be offered.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</sections>
