<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header$ -->
<!-- English CVS version: 1.47 -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/zh_cn/utf-8.xml" lang="zh_cn" disclaimer="draft">
<title>在 Gentoo 下使用 UTF-8</title>

<author title="作者">
  <mail link="slarti@gentoo.org">Thomas Martin</mail>
</author>
<author title="贡献者">
  <mail link="devil@gentoo.org.ua">Alexander Simonov</mail>
</author>
<author title="编辑">
  <mail link="fox2mike@gentoo.org">Shyam Mani</mail>
</author>
<author title="译者">
  <mail link="goldenshore999@gmail.com">周骞</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
这个指南将会向你展示如何在Gentoo Linux系统下设置以及使用 UTF-8 Unicode 字符集。
在此之前，先把Unicode的好处阐述一下，然后针对 UTF-8 论述。
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license />

<version>2.25</version>
<date>2007-04-17</date>

<chapter>
<title>字符编码</title>
<section>
<title>什么是字符编码</title>
<body>

<p>
电脑本身是不认识文字的。相反的，每一个字符都是用一个数字来表示。在以前，每一组
用来表示字母和和字符的数字（也称作编码系统，编码或者字符集）都会被电脑硬件的限
制而在大小上被限制。

Computers do not understand text themselves. Instead, every character is
represented by a number. Traditionally, each set of numbers used to represent
alphabets and characters (known as a coding system, encoding or character set)
was limited in size due to limitations in computer hardware.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>字符编码的历史</title>
<body>

<p>
最普遍的（至少最被广泛接受的）字符集是 <b>ASCII</b> (美国信息互换标准代码)。
很多人都认为ASCII是最成功的软件标准。现代ASCII编码是在1986年被美国国家标准协会
统一的。
</p>

<p>
ASCII是严格限制在的7比特大小，就是她会用7位二进制数的组合来表示数字，在十进制中
范围是从0到127。他们包括了32个不可视的控制字符，大多数是从0到31之间的范围，还有
就是结束控制字符以及位处127的DEL/删除字符。从32到126的都是可视字符：空格，标点，
拉丁字母和数字。

ASCII is strictly seven-bit, meaning that it uses bit patterns representable
with seven binary digits, which provides a range of 0 to 127 in decimal. These
include 32 non-visible control characters, most between 0 and 31, with the
final control character, DEL or delete at 127.  Characters 32 to 126 are
visible characters: a space, punctuation marks, Latin letters and numbers.
</p>

<p>
ASCII中的第八位原来是用来作为校验的奇偶位。如果不需要的话则置为0。这样的话，每一个
ASCII字符都可以用一个字节表示。

The eighth bit in ASCII was originally used as a parity bit for error checking.
If this is not desired, it is left as 0. This means that, with ASCII, each
character is represented by a single byte.
</p>

<p>
虽然在现代英语通讯中ASCII已经足够了，但是其他的欧洲语言中所包括的特色字符就不那
么容易解决了。开发出 ISO 8859 标准就是用来解决这些需求的。他们向后和ASCII兼容，
但是与ASCII不同，第八位没有被留空，而是用来给相应的编码增加127个位置。ISO 8859的
限制迎来了曙光，现在已经有15种ISO 8859标准的变种（8859-1到8859-15)。除了在ASCII
兼容的范围内的字节外，同样字节表示的字符会经常出现冲突。为了让交互性情况更复杂，
微软的某些版本的Windows使用Windows-1252编码，而不是西欧语言编码。这个是
ISO 8859-1编码的超集，但是却有那么几个不同。但是幸亏，他们都和ASCII编码兼容。

Although ASCII was enough for communication in modern English, in other
European languages that include accented characters, things were not so easy.
The ISO 8859 standards were developed to meet these needs.  They were backwards
compatible with ASCII, but instead of leaving the eighth bit blank, they used
it to allow another 127 characters in each encoding. ISO 8859's limitations
soon came to light, and there are currently 15 variants of the ISO 8859
standard (8859-1 through to 8859-15).  Outside of the ASCII-compatible byte
range of these character sets, there is often conflict between the letters
represented by each byte. To complicate interoperability between character
encodings further, Windows-1252 is used in some versions of Microsoft Windows
instead for Western European languages. This is a superset of ISO 8859-1,
however it is different in several ways. These sets do all retain ASCII
compatibility, however.
</p>

<p>
在其他操作系统仍然为同一个语言使用不同字符集的时候，如 Shift-JIS 和 
ISO-2022-JP，开发完全不同的单字节编码，如为非拉丁字母日文韩文（以及在一定程度上
的中文）开发的EUC（扩展UNIX编码）编码，会增加更多的混乱。那些查看斯拉夫语
(cyrillic)象形文字的用户需要在俄罗斯人和保加利亚人用的KOI8-R和乌克兰人用的
KOI8-U之间选择，或者其他的斯拉夫语编码体系如失败的ISO 8859-5编码，以及常见的
Windows-1251编码等。所有的这些字符集几乎和ASCII的都有兼容问题（虽然KOI8编码把斯
拉夫语字符按照拉丁顺序排列，这样如果第八位被去掉的话，这些字符一样可以在ASCII终
端中通过意译去解读。

The necessary development of completely different single-byte encodings for
non-Latin alphabets, such as EUC (Extended Unix Coding) which is used for
Japanese and Korean (and to a lesser extent Chinese) created more confusion,
while other operating systems still used different character sets for the same
languages, for example, Shift-JIS and ISO-2022-JP.  Users wishing to view
cyrillic glyphs had to choose between KOI8-R for Russian and Bulgarian or
KOI8-U for Ukrainian, as well as all the other cyrillic encodings such as the
unsuccessful ISO 8859-5, and the common Windows-1251 set. All of these
character sets broke most compatibility with ASCII (although KOI8 encodings
place cyrillic characters in Latin order, so in case the eighth bit is
stripped, text is still decipherable on an ASCII terminal through case-reversed
transliteration.)
</p>

<p>
这带来了混乱，而且对于多语言交互来说是几乎不能胜任的，尤其在不同字母的情况下。
接下来， Unicode。

This has led to confusion, and also to an almost total inability for
multilingual communication, especially across different alphabets. Enter
Unicode.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>什么是Unicode?</title>
<body>

<p>
Unicode克服了传统字符集的单字节限制。她有17个“位面”，每个位面有65,536个代码点
总共可以装下1,114,112个字符。第一个位面，也叫"基本多文种平面"或BMP，包括了几乎
所有你会用到的东西，很多人误认为Unicode是一个16位的字符集。

Unicode throws away the traditional single-byte limit of character sets.  It
uses 17 "planes" of 65,536 code points to describe a maximum of 1,114,112
characters. As the first plane, aka. "Basic Multilingual Plane" or BMP,
contains almost everything you will ever use, many have made the wrong
assumption that Unicode was a 16-bit character set.
</p>

<p>
Unicode可以用多种方式去表示，但是两个最普遍的方法是<b>UTF</b>（Unicode
Transformation Format，Unicode转换格式）和<b>UCS</b>（Universal Character Set，
通用字符集）。跟在UTF后边的一个数字指定了一个单元中的比特数，而UCS则是字节数。
因为UTF-8的整8位特性，她已成为最广泛传播的Unicode文字交互手段，她也是本文的主题。

Unicode has been mapped in many different ways, but the two most common are
<b>UTF</b> (Unicode Transformation Format) and <b>UCS</b> (Universal Character
Set). A number after UTF indicates the number of bits in one unit, while the
number after UCS indicates the number of bytes. UTF-8 has become the most
widespread means for the interchange of Unicode text as a result of its
eight-bit clean nature, and it is the subject of this document.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UTF-8</title>
<body>

<p>
UTF-8是一个变长的字符编码，也就是说她会用1到4个字节去表示一个符号。这样，第一
个UTF-8的字节是用来编码ASCII的，这样也就让她可以和ASCII完全兼容。UTF-8意味着在
数据体积增加少许后ASCII和拉丁字母可以互相交互，因为只用了第一个比特。东方字符
如日本字的用户，很不爽得被分配到了更高的字节范围，因为这样会造成最多50％数据的
重复。

UTF-8 is a variable-length character encoding, which in this instance means
that it uses 1 to 4 bytes per symbol. So, the first UTF-8 byte is used for
encoding ASCII, giving the character set full backwards compatibility with
ASCII. UTF-8 means that ASCII and Latin characters are interchangeable with
little increase in the size of the data, because only the first bit is used.
Users of Eastern alphabets such as Japanese, who have been assigned a higher
byte range are unhappy, as this results in as much as a 50% redundancy in their
data.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UTF-8能为你做什么</title>
<body>

<p>
UTF-8允许你在一个符合标准的和国际多文字环境中工作，并且不会产生过多的数据重复。
UTF-8是在Internet上，Email中，IRC还有几乎其他所有媒体中传输非ASCII字符的首选方
法。尽管如此，很多人还是认为在线交流用UTF-8是属于滥用。在讨论频道，邮件列表和新
闻组中用<e>非ASCII</e>UTF8之前，最好注意他们对UTF-8的态度。

UTF-8 allows you to work in a standards-compliant and internationally accepted
multilingual environment, with a comparatively low data redundancy. UTF-8 is
the preferred way for transmitting non-ASCII characters over the Internet,
through Email, IRC or almost any other medium. Despite this, many people regard
UTF-8 in online communication as abusive. It is always best to be aware of the
attitude towards UTF-8 in a specific channel, mailing list or Usenet group
before using <e>non-ASCII</e> UTF-8.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Linux中设置UTF-8</title>
<section>
<title>查找或建立UTF-8场所(Locale)</title>
<body>

<p>
现在你已经理解Unicode的原理了，就可以在你的系统中开始使用UTF-8了。
Now that you understand the principles behind Unicode, you're ready to start
using UTF-8 with your system.
</p>

<p>
使用UTF-8的初步要求是要有一个支持国家语言支持(NLS)的glibc。推荐的方法是设置文件
<path>/etc/locale.gen</path>。关于如何使用这个文件并不在这个文档涉及的范围内，可
以在<uri link="/doc/en/guide-localization.xml#doc_chap3_sect3">Gentoo 本地化指南
</uri>。

The preliminary requirement for UTF-8 is to have a version of glibc installed
that has national language support. The recommend means to do this is the
<path>/etc/locale.gen</path> file. It is beyond the scope of this document to
explain the usage of this file though. It is explained in the <uri
link="/doc/en/guide-localization.xml#doc_chap3_sect3">Gentoo Localization
Guide</uri>.
</p>

<p>
下一步，我们需要判断对应我们语言的UTF-8 locale是否已经存在，还是需要去创建。

Next, we'll need to decide whether a UTF-8 locale is already available for our
language, or whether we need to create one.
</p>

<pre caption="检查 UTF-8 locale 是否已经存在">
<comment>（把"en_GB"替换成你想要的locale设置）</comment>
# <i>locale -a | grep 'en_GB'</i>
en_GB
en_GB.UTF-8
</pre>

<p>
我们需要从这条命令的结果中提取结尾类似<c>.UTF-8</c>的行。如果没有结尾是像<c>
.UTF-8</c>结尾的行，那么我们需要创建一个兼容UTF-8的locale.

From the output of this command line, we need to take the result with a suffix
similar to <c>.UTF-8</c>. If there is no result with a suffix similar to
<c>.UTF-8</c>, we need to create a UTF-8 compatible locale.
</p>

<note>
只有在你的语言没有相应的UTF-8 locale的时候才运行以下命令。

Only execute the following code listing if you do not have a UTF-8 locale
available for your language.
</note>

<pre caption="创建一个UTF-8 locale">
<comment>（把"en_GB"替换成你想要的locale设置）</comment>
# <i>localedef -i en_GB -f UTF-8 en_GB.UTF-8</i>
</pre>

<p>
另外一个指定UTF-8 locale的方法就是在文件<path>/etc/locale.gen</path>中增添相应
的locale，然后运行命令<c>locale-gen</c>生成需要的locale。

Another way to include a UTF-8 locale is to add it to the
<path>/etc/locale.gen</path> file and generate necessary locales with
<c>locale-gen</c> command.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/locale.gen 其中一行">
en_GB.UTF-8 UTF-8
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>设置Locale</title>
<body>

<p>
要使用新locale我们需要设置一个环境变量：<c>LANG</c>（你可以通过设置<c>LC_ALL
</c>变量来覆盖这个变量）。还有其他很多不同的方法去设置；有的人倾向针对某一个
用户设置UTF-8环境，这时候他们需要在他们自己的<path>~/.profile</path>中设置，
（如果用<c>/bin/sh</c>的话）；或者如果你用<c>/bin/bash</c>的话，就在<path>
~/.bash_profile</path>或者<path>~/.bashrc</path>设置。

There is one environment variable that needs to be set in order to use our new
UTF-8 locales: <c>LANG</c> (you can override this variable with the
<c>LC_ALL</c> setting as well). There are also many different ways to set it;
some people prefer to only have a UTF-8 environment for a specific user, in
which case they set them in their <path>~/.profile</path> (if you use
<c>/bin/sh</c>), <path>~/.bash_profile</path> or <path>~/.bashrc</path> (if you
use <c>/bin/bash</c>).
</p>

<p>
其他的则选择设置全局locale。有一种特殊的情况作者是特别推荐的，就是在使用
<path>/etc/init.d/xdm</path>的时候，因为这个启动脚本会在任何shell启动文件
被source(引入)前启动显示管理器和桌面，这样也就是比任何环境变量都要早。

Others prefer to set the locale globally. One specific circumstance where 
the author particularly recommends doing this is when 
<path>/etc/init.d/xdm</path> is in use, because
this init script starts the display manager and desktop before any of the
aforementioned shell startup files are sourced, and so before any of the
variables are in the environment.
</p>

<p>
全局local设置应该在文件<path>/etc/env.d/02locale</path>中完成。这个文件看起来
应该和以下内容类似：

Setting the locale globally should be done using
<path>/etc/env.d/02locale</path>. The file should look something like the
following:
</p>

<pre caption="Demonstration /etc/env.d/02locale">
<comment>（不用再说了，把你的locale代替掉"en_GB.UTF-8"）</comment>
LANG="en_GB.UTF-8"
</pre>

<note>
你可以用<c>LC_ALL</c>代替<c>LANG</c>。这个会把locale的所有分类都设置上，包括数
字和币种等。在很少情况下，这会引起一些问题。但是，大多数用户应该是不会因使用
<c>LC_ALL</c>而碰到问题。关于<c>LC_ALL</c>影响到的分类的信息，请阅读<uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/libc/manual/html_node/Locale-Categories.html#Locale-Categories">
GNU locale页</uri>。

You can also substitute <c>LC_ALL</c> for <c>LANG</c>. This sets your locale
for all categories, including numerical and currency values. On a very few
systems, it might cause some issues. However, most users should be able to use
<c>LC_ALL</c> without problems. For more information on the categories affected
by using <c>LC_ALL</c>, please read the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/libc/manual/html_node/Locale-Categories.html#Locale-Categories">GNU
locale page</uri>.
</note>

<p>
下一步，环境必须要为之前的改变更新。

Next, the environment must be updated with the change.
</p>

<pre caption="更新环境">
# <i>env-update</i>
>>> Regenerating /etc/ld.so.cache...
 * Caching service dependencies ...
# <i>source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
现在，不带参数的运行<c>locale</c>命令，看看我们是否已经正确设置了环境变量。

Now, run <c>locale</c> with no arguments to see if we have the correct
variables in our environment:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking if our new locale is in the environment">
# <i>locale</i>
LANG=
LC_CTYPE="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_NUMERIC="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_TIME="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_COLLATE="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_MONETARY="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_MESSAGES="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_PAPER="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_NAME="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_ADDRESS="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_TELEPHONE="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_MEASUREMENT="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_IDENTIFICATION="en_GB.UTF-8"
LC_ALL=en_GB.UTF-8
</pre>

<p>
好了。你已经在使用UTF-8 locale了，下一个麻烦就是配置你的日用程序了。

That's everything. You are now using UTF-8 locales, and the next hurdle is the
configuration of the applications you use from day to day.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>应用支持</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
当Unicode刚开始在软件世界得到动力的时候，多字节字符集和被用来写日常使用的程序的
C等语言不是很合拍。即使是今天，有的程序仍然不能正确处理UTF-8。幸运的是，大多数
都没问题！

When Unicode first started gaining momentum in the software world, multibyte
character sets were not well suited to languages like C, in which many of the
day-to-day programs people use are written.  Even today, some programs are not
able to handle UTF-8 properly.  Fortunately, most are!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>文件名，NTFS和FAT</title>
<body>

<p>
在内核选项中，有那么几个NLS选项，但是千万别被混淆了。大多数情况下，你只需要在
内核中加入UTF-8 NLS支持，以及将默认的NLS选项设置成utf8就可以了。

There are several NLS options in the Linux kernel configuration menu, but it is
important to not become confused! For the most part, the only thing you need to
do is to build UTF-8 NLS support into your kernel, and change the default NLS
option to utf8.
</p>

<pre caption="UTF-8 NLS的内核配置步骤">
File Systems --&gt;
  Native Language Support --&gt;
    (utf8) Default NLS Option
    &lt;*&gt; NLS UTF8
    <comment>(Also &lt;*&gt; other character sets that are in use in
    your FAT filesystems or Joilet CD-ROMs.)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
如果你计划加载NTFS分区，你也许需要为mount指定一个<c>nls=</c>选项。如果你计划加载
FAT分区，你也许需要为mount指定一个<c>codepage=</c>选项。你也可以在内核配置中为
FAT设置一个默认的codepage。注意，mount命令中指定的<c>codepage</c>会覆盖内核中
的设置。

If you plan on mounting NTFS partitions, you may need to specify an <c>nls=</c>
option with mount. If you plan on mounting FAT partitions, you may need to
specify a <c>codepage=</c> option with mount. Optionally, you can also set a
default codepage for FAT in the kernel configuration. Note that the
<c>codepage</c> option with mount will override the kernel settings.
</p>

<pre caption="内核中的FAT设置">
File Systems --&gt;
  DOS/FAT/NT Filesystems  --&gt;
    (437) Default codepage for fat
</pre>

<p>
你应该避免把<c>Default iocharset for fat</c>设置成UTF-8，因为这个是不推荐的。相
反，你可以在mount的时候加入选项utf8=true。可以从<c>man mount</c>和内核文档
<path>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/filesystems/vfat.txt</path>获取更多相关的信
息。

You should avoid setting <c>Default iocharset for fat</c> to UTF-8, as it is
not recommended. Instead, you may want to pass the option utf8=true when
mounting your FAT partitions. For further information, see <c>man mount</c> and
the kernel documentation at
<path>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/filesystems/vfat.txt</path>.
</p>

<p>
如果想改变文件名的编码，可以用<c>app-text/convmv</c>。
For changing the encoding of filenames, <c>app-text/convmv</c> can be used.
</p>

<pre caption="convmv使用例子">
# <i>emerge --ask app-text/convmv</i>
<comment>（命令格式）</comment>
# <i>convmv -f &lt;current-encoding&gt; -t utf-8 &lt;filename&gt;</i>
<comment>（把iso-8859-1换成你想要的原始编码）</comment>
# <i>convmv -f iso-8859-1 -t utf-8 filename</i>
</pre>

<p>
如果想改变文件<e>内容</e>，那么请使用由<c>glibc</c>提供的工具<c>iconv</c>。

For changing the <e>contents</e> of files, use the <c>iconv</c> utility,
bundled with <c>glibc</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="iconv使用例子">
<comment>（把iso-8859-1换成你想要的原始编码）</comment>
<comment>（检查输出是否合法）</comment>
# <i>iconv -f iso-8859-1 -t utf-8 filename</i> 
<comment>（要转换文件，你必须创建一个新文件）</comment>
# <i>iconv -f iso-8859-1 -t utf-8 filename > newfile</i>
</pre>

<p>
<c>app-text/recode</c> 也可以用来做这个事情。
<c>app-text/recode</c> can also be used for this purpose.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>系统终端</title>
<body>

<impo>
在终端用Uicode，你需要>=sys-apps/baselayout-1.11.9。
You need >=sys-apps/baselayout-1.11.9 for Unicode on the console.
</impo>

<p>
在终端下开启UTF-8，你要编辑<path>/etc/rc.conf</path>并且设置<c>UNICODE="yes"
</c>，还要阅读该文件内相应的注释－－如果你想好好发觉Unicode，那么一个带有足够
字的字体是很重要的。为了不出错，确定你已经按照<uri link="#doc_chap1">第一章
</uri>中所说正确得建立了一个Unicode locale。

To enable UTF-8 on the console, you should edit <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> and
set <c>UNICODE="yes"</c>, and also read the comments in that file -- it is
important to have a font that has a good range of characters if you plan on
making the most of Unicode. For this to work, make sure you have properly
created a Unicode locale as explained in <uri link="#doc_chap1">Chapter 1</uri>.
</p>

<p>
<path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path>中的<c>KEYMAP</c>变量，应该是一个Unicode
keymap.
The <c>KEYMAP</c> variable, set in <path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path>, should
have a Unicode keymap specified. 
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/conf.d/keymaps 例子片段">
<comment>（把 "uk" 替换成你自己键盘的布局）</comment>
KEYMAP="uk"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ncurses和Slang</title>
<body>

<note>
如果你没安装或者不用Slang的话，忽略这段中相关Slang的信息。

Ignore any mention of Slang in this section if you do not have it installed or
do not use it.
</note>

<p>
在<path>/etc/make.conf</path>里边的全局USE标记中加入<c>unicode</c>是很明智的，
然后再根据需要重新emerge <c>sys-libs/ncurses</c>和<c>sys-libs/slang</c>。
Portage在升级你的系统时也会自动帮你搞定的。

It is wise to add <c>unicode</c> to your global USE flags in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>, and then to remerge <c>sys-libs/ncurses</c> and
<c>sys-libs/slang</c> if appropriate. Portage will do this automatically when
you update your system:
</p>

<pre caption="升级你的系统">
# <i>emerge --update --deep --newuse world</i>
</pre>

<p>
我们还需要重新编译依赖这些包的包，这样USE的改变就会被应用。我们用到的工具
（<c>revdep-rebuild</c>）是包<c>gentoolkit</c>的一部分。

We also need to rebuild packages that link to these, now the USE changes have
been applied. The tool we use (<c>revdep-rebuild</c>) is part of the
<c>gentoolkit</c> package.
</p>

<pre caption="重新编译连接到ncurses或者slang的程序">
# <i>revdep-rebuild --soname libncurses.so.5</i>
# <i>revdep-rebuild --soname libslang.so.1</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>KDE，GNOME和Xfce</title>
<body>

<p>
所有主流桌面系统都完全支持Unicode，除了之前已经提及的设置外也不需要进一步设置
什么了。这是因为底层的图形工具包（Qt或GTK+2）已经支持UTF-8。这样，所有由这些工
具包写出来的程序都是原生的支持UTF-8的。

All of the major desktop environments have full Unicode support, and will
require no further setup than what has already been covered in this guide. This
is because the underlying graphical toolkits (Qt or GTK+2) are UTF-8 aware.
Subsequently, all applications running on top of these toolkits should be
UTF-8-aware out of the box.
</p>

<p>
当然，也有例外，比如的Xlib和GTK+1。GTK+1需要在~/.gtkrc里边有一个iso-10646-1的
字体设置，例如<c>-misc-fixed-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-iso10646-1</c>。还有就是使用
Xlib或者Xaw的程序需要有类似的设置，不然他们会罢工的。

The exceptions to this rule come in Xlib and GTK+1. GTK+1 requires a
iso-10646-1 FontSpec in the ~/.gtkrc, for example
<c>-misc-fixed-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-iso10646-1</c>. Also, applications using
Xlib or Xaw will need to be given a similar FontSpec, otherwise they will not
work.
</p>

<note>
如果你安装了Gnome1 Control Center的某个版本的话，就用她来设置好了。选任何一个
iso10646-1的字体就可以了。

If you have a version of the gnome1 control center around, use that instead.
Pick any iso10646-1 font from there.
</note>

<pre caption="例子 ~/.gtkrc (为GTK+1) 定义兼容Unicode的字体">
style "user-font"
{
    fontset="-misc-fixed-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-iso10646-1"
}
widget_class "*" style "user-font"
</pre>

<p>
如果有一个程序同时支持Qt和GTK+2的图形界面，那么GTK+2的图形界面应该会更好的支持
Unicode。

If an application has support for both a Qt and GTK+2 GUI, the GTK+2 GUI will
generally give better results with Unicode.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>X11和字体</title>
<body>

<impo>
<c>x11-base/xorg-x11</c>对Unicode的支持比XFree86更好，<e>极度</e>推荐。

<c>x11-base/xorg-x11</c> has far better support for Unicode than XFree86
and is <e>highly</e> recommended.
</impo>

<p>
TrueType字体支持Unicode，而且Xorg自带的大多数字体都有很好的字符支持，当然，他
们也不可能把每一个Unicode字型都提供了。要为X提供东亚字符支持（包括Bitstream
Vera字体集合）的话，记得在USE标记中加入<c>cjk</c>。很多其他的程序也使用这个use，
所以很值得把她加入永久的USE标记。

TrueType fonts have support for Unicode, and most of the fonts that ship with
Xorg have impressive character support, although, obviously, not every single
glyph available in Unicode has been created for that font. To build fonts
(including the Bitstream Vera set) with support for East Asian letters with X,
make sure you have the <c>cjk</c> USE flag set. Many other applications utilise
this flag, so it may be worthwhile to add it as a permanent USE flag.
</p>

<p>
还有，Porage有几个字体包也支持Unicode。

Also, several font packages in Portage are Unicode aware.
</p>

<pre caption="可选：安装一些支持Unicode的字体">
# <i>emerge terminus-font intlfonts freefonts cronyx-fonts corefonts</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>窗口管理器和终端模拟器</title>
<body>

<p>
不基于GTK或Qt的窗口管理器一般都会有很不错的Unicode支持，因为他们一般都用Xft库
来处理字体的。如果你的窗口管理器不用Xft处理字体，你仍然可以把之前提及的字体设
置作为Unicode字体使用。(就是<c>-misc-fixed-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-*-iso10646-1</c>)

Window managers not built on GTK or Qt generally have very good Unicode
support, as they often use the Xft library for handling fonts. If your window
manager does not use Xft for fonts, you can still use the FontSpec mentioned in
the previous section as a Unicode font.
</p>

<p>
使用Xft并支持Unicode的终端模拟器更难获得。除了Konsole和gnome-terminal外，
Portage中最好的选择就是<c>x11-terms/rxvt-unicode</c>，<c>xfce-extra/terminal
</c>，<c>gnustep-apps/terminal</c>，<c>x11-terms/mlterm</c>，或者编译时带了
<c>unicode</c>USE的<c>x11-terms/xterm</c>并且用<c>uxterm</c>启动。
<c>app-misc/screen</c>在用<c>screen -U</c>启动的时候也支持UTF-8的，或者将以下内
容加入到<path>~/.screenrc</path>：

Terminal emulators that use Xft and support Unicode are harder to come by.
Aside from Konsole and gnome-terminal, the best options in Portage are
<c>x11-terms/rxvt-unicode</c>, <c>xfce-extra/terminal</c>,
<c>gnustep-apps/terminal</c>, <c>x11-terms/mlterm</c>, or plain
<c>x11-terms/xterm</c> when built with the <c>unicode</c> USE flag and invoked
as <c>uxterm</c>. <c>app-misc/screen</c> supports UTF-8 too, when invoked as
<c>screen -U</c> or the following is put into the <path>~/.screenrc</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="~/.screenrc for UTF-8">
defutf8 on
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Vim，Emacs，Xemacs和Nano</title>
<body>

<p>
Vim完全支持UTF-8，而且还有内置UTF-8文件检测。可以用<c>:help mbyte.txt</c>获取
更多的信息。

Vim provides full UTF-8 support, and also has builtin detection of UTF-8 files. 
For further information in Vim, use <c>:help mbyte.txt</c>.
</p>

<p>
Emacs 22.x 以及更高的版本也完全支持UTF-8。Xemacs 22.x暂时还不支持组合字符。

Emacs 22.x and higher has full UTF-8 support as well. Xemacs 22.x does not
support combining characters yet. 
</p>

<p>
低版本的Emacs和Xemacs也许需要安装<c>app-emacs/mule-ucs</c>或
<c>app-xemacs/mule-ucs</c>，然后把以下内容加入到<path>~/.emacs</path>来获得对
UTF-8中CJK（中日韩）语言的支持。

Lower versions of Emacs and/or Xemacs might require you to install 
<c>app-emacs/mule-ucs</c> and/or <c>app-xemacs/mule-ucs</c>
and add the following code to your <path>~/.emacs</path> to have support for CJK
languages in UTF-8:
</p>

<pre caption="Emacs CJK UTF-8 支持">
(require 'un-define)
(require 'jisx0213)
(set-language-environment "Japanese")
(set-default-coding-systems 'utf-8)
(set-terminal-coding-system 'utf-8)
</pre>

<p>
Nano从1.3.6版本以后都完全支持UTF-8的。

Nano has provided full UTF-8 support since version 1.3.6.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Shells</title>
<body>

<p>
现在，<c>bash</c>通过GNU readline库完全支持Unicode。Z Shell（<c>zsh</c>）如果
有<c>unicode</c>USE标志的话，也可以提供Unicode支持。

Currently, <c>bash</c> provides full Unicode support through the GNU readline
library. Z Shell (<c>zsh</c>) offers Unicode support with the <c>unicode</c> USE
flag.
</p>

<p>
C shell，<c>tcsh</c>和<c>ksh</c>完全不支持UTF-8的。

The C shell, <c>tcsh</c> and <c>ksh</c> do not provide UTF-8 support at all.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Irssi</title>
<body>

<p>
Irssi完全支持UTF-8，虽然她还是要求用户去设置一个选项。

Irssi has complete UTF-8 support, although it does require a user
to set an option.
</p>

<pre caption="为Irssi开启UTF-8">
/set term_charset UTF-8
</pre>

<p>
那些把非ASCII字符按非UTF-8字处理的频道，可以用<c>/recode</c>命令来转换这些字符。
输入<c>/help recode</c>可以获取更多信息。
For channels where non-ASCII characters are often exchanged in non-UTF-8
charsets, the <c>/recode</c> command may be used to convert the characters.
Type <c>/help recode</c> for more information.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mutt</title>
<body>

<p>
Mutt邮件用户代理有很不错的Unicode支持。你不需要在配置文件中加入任何东西就可以
让Mutt支持UTF-8。如果你的配置文件（包括签名）都是UTF-8编码的话，Mutt不需要任何
修改就可以在Unicode环境中正确工作。

The Mutt mail user agent has very good Unicode support. To use UTF-8 with Mutt,
you don't need to put anything in your configuration files. Mutt will work
under unicode enviroment without modification if all your configuration files
(signature included) are UTF-8 encoded.
</p>

<note>
你也许还会在用Mutt阅读邮件的时候看到'?'。这是有人用的邮件客户端没有正确的指出
所用的字符集。除了让他们好好配置软件外似乎没什么别的方法了。

You may still see '?' in mail you read with Mutt. This is a result of people
using a mail client which does not indicate the used charset. You can't do much
about this than to ask them to configure their client correctly.
</note>

<p>
可以参考<uri link="http://wiki.mutt.org/index.cgi?MuttFaq/Charset">Mutt Wiki
</uri>获取更多信息。

Further information is available from the <uri
link="http://wiki.mutt.org/index.cgi?MuttFaq/Charset">Mutt Wiki</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Man</title>
<body>

<p>
Man页面是任何Linux机器都包括的部分。为了确保man页面中的Unicode字符被正确渲染，
文件<path>/etc/man.conf</path>中的一行需要被替换：

Man pages are an integral part of any Linux machine. To ensure that any 
unicode in your man pages render correctly, edit <path>/etc/man.conf</path> 
and replace a line as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="man.conf的Unicod支持">
<comment>（原始）</comment>
NROFF           /usr/bin/nroff -Tascii -c -mandoc
<comment>（替换后）</comment>
NROFF           /usr/bin/nroff -mandoc -c
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>elinks和links</title>
<body>

<p>
这些是常用的基于文本的浏览器，我们看看怎么为她们打开UTF-8支持。在<c>elinks</c>
和<c>links</c>中，有两个方法的，浏览器中Setup选项设置或者直接修改配置文件。要
在Setup选项中设置的话，首先用<c>elinks</c>或<c>links</c>打开一个网站，然后按
<c>Alt+S</c>进入Setup菜单，再选择Terminal选项，或者按T。下拉到最后一个选项
<c>UTF-8 I/O</c>并且按回车选择她。然后保存并且离开菜单。<c>links</c>中你也许需
要再按一次<c>Alt+S</c>然后按<c>S</c>来保存设置。要在配置文件中改变，请看以下内
容。

These are commonly used text-based browsers, and we shall see how we can enable
UTF-8 support on them. On <c>elinks</c> and <c>links</c>, there are two ways to
go about this, one using the Setup option from within the browser or editing the
config file. To set the option through the browser, open a site with
<c>elinks</c> or <c>links</c> and then <c>Alt+S</c> to enter the Setup Menu then
select Terminal options, or press <c>T</c>. Scroll down and select the last
option <c>UTF-8 I/O</c> by pressing Enter. Then Save and exit the menu. On
<c>links</c> you may have to do a repeat <c>Alt+S</c> and then press <c>S</c> to
save. The config file option, is shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="为elinks/links开启UTF-8">
<comment>（elinks的话，编辑/etc/elinks/elinks.conf或者~/.elinks/elinks.conf，
把以下这行加入到文件里）</comment>
set terminal.linux.utf_8_io = 1

<comment>（links的话，编辑~/.links/links.cfg，把以下这样加入到文件中）</comment>
terminal "xterm" 0 1 0 us-ascii utf-8
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Samba</title>
<body>

<p>
Samba是一套为UNIX系统，如Macs,Linux和FreeBSD，而实现SMB（服务器消息块）协议的软
件。这个协议有的时候也会被称作公共Internet文件系统（CIFS）。Samba也包括了
NetBIOS系统－Windows网络中用来文件共享的。
Samba is a software suite which implements the SMB (Server Message Block)
protocol for UNIX systems such as Macs, Linux and FreeBSD. The protocol
is also sometimes referred to as the Common Internet File System (CIFS). Samba
also includes the NetBIOS system - used for file sharing over windows networks.
</p>

<pre caption="为Samba开启UTF-8">
<comment>（编辑/etc/samba/smb.conf，把以下内容添加到[global]部分）</comment>
dos charset = 1255
unix charset = UTF-8
display charset = UTF-8
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>测试</title>
<body>

<p>
Internet有很多UTF-8测试网站的。<c>net-www/w3m</c>，<c>net-www/links</c>，<c>
net-www/elinks</c>，<c>net-www/lynx</c>和其他基于Mozilla的浏览器（包括火狐）都
支持UTF-8。Konqourer和Opera也完全支持UTF-8。

There are numerous UTF-8 test websites around.  <c>net-www/w3m</c>,
<c>net-www/links</c>, <c>net-www/elinks</c>, <c>net-www/lynx</c> and all
Mozilla based browsers (including Firefox) support UTF-8. Konqueror and Opera
have full UTF-8 support too.
</p>

<p>
当使用那些纯文本Web浏览器的时候，一定要确保所在的终端也支持Unicode。

When using one of the text-only web browsers, make absolutely sure you are
using a Unicode-aware terminal.
</p>

<p>
如果你看到某些字符显示为一个小方框并且中间有字母或者数字的，那么就是说你的字体
没有UTF-8想要的相应的符号或者字型。所以就用一个方框代替，并且里边是对应该字符
的UTF-8的十六进制码。
If you see certain characters displayed as boxes with letters or numbers
inside, this means that your font does not have a character for the symbol or
glyph that the UTF-8 wants. Instead, it displays a box with the hex code of the
UTF-8 symbol.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.w3.org/2001/06/utf-8-test/UTF-8-demo.html">一个W3C 
    UTF-8测试页面</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://titus.uni-frankfurt.de/indexe.htm?/unicode/unitest.htm">
    一个UTF-8测试页面，由法兰克福大学提供</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>输入法</title>
<body>

<p>
在X中<e>Dead keys</e>可以用来输入一些不包括在你键盘上的字符。方法是按下你的右
Alt键（在有的国家也叫AltGr），同时你也可以选择多按一个回车以左的非字母键（修改
键）_，然后松开他们，最后按一个字母键。这样Dead key应该会修改她的了。在按下
AltGr以及修改键的时候，Shift键也可以被用来进一步修改输入内容。

<e>Dead keys</e> may be used to input characters in X that are not included on
your keyboard. These work by pressing your right Alt key (or in some countries,
AltGr) and an optional key from the non-alphabetical section of the keyboard to
the left of the return key at once, releasing them, and then pressing a letter.
The dead key should modify it. Input can be further modified by using the Shift
key at the same time as pressing the AltGr and modifier.
</p>

<p>
在X中开启Deak Keys，你需要一个支持她的布局。大多数欧洲布局都默认有Dead key支持
的，但是，北美布局似乎并不是这样。虽然在一定程度上不同的布局有不一致的地方，但
是简单的解决方法似乎就是例如直接指定"en_US"布局而不是"us"布局。布局是在文件
<path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path>里边这样设置的：

To enable dead keys in X, you need a layout that supports it. Most European
layouts already have dead keys with the default variant.  However, this is not
true of North American layouts. Although there is a degree of inconsistency
between layouts, the easiest solution seems to be to use a layout in the form
"en_US" rather than "us", for example. The layout is set in
<path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path> like so:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/X11/xorg.conf snippet">
Section "InputDevice"
    Identifier "Keyboard0"
    Driver     "kbd"
    Option     "XkbLayout" "en_US" <comment># 而不是仅仅 "us"</comment>
    <comment>（其他 Xkb 选项可以放这里）</comment>
EndSection
</pre>

<note>
如果你是北美布局或者你的布局Dead key不工作的时候才需要做之前的这个修改。欧洲用
户的Deak keys应该是直接就可以用的。

The preceding change only needs to be applied if you are using a North American
layout, or another layout where dead keys do not seem to be working. European
users should have working dead keys as is.
</note>

<p>
这个修改要在X服务重新启动后才会生效。要是你想马上生效的话，用<c>setxkbmap</c>
工具。比如<c>setxkbmap en_US</c>。

This change will come into effect when your X server is restarted. To apply the
change now, use the <c>setxkbmap</c> tool, for example, <c>setxkbmap en_US</c>.
</p>

<p>
对Dead keys的描述也许通过例子是最简单的。虽然结果是根据locale而变化的，但是概
念是不变的。例子中包括了UTF-8，所以你需要告诉你的浏览器用UTF-8模式浏览，或者有
一个已经配置好的UTF-8 locale。
It is probably easiest to describe dead keys with examples. Although the
results are locale dependent, the concepts should remain the same regardless of
locale. The examples contain UTF-8, so to view them you need to either tell
your browser to view the page as UTF-8, or have a UTF-8 locale already
configured.
</p>

<p>
同时按下键AltGr和键[，松开，再按键a，就可以得到字符ä。
同时按下键AltGr和键[，松开，再按键e，就可以得到字符ë。
同时按下键AltGr和键;，松开，再按键a，就可以得到字符á。
同时按下键AltGr和键;，松开，再按键e，就可以得到字符é。

When I press AltGr and [ at once, release them, and then press a, 'ä' is
produced. When I press AltGr and [ at once, and then press e, 'ë' is produced.
When I press AltGr and ; at once, 'á' is produced, and when I press AltGr and ;
at once, release them, and then press e, 'é' is produced.
</p>

<p>
同时按下键AltGr，Shift和[，松开，再按键a，得到一个北欧Scandinavian å。类似的，
同时按下键AltGr，Shift和[，但是<e>只</e>松开[，然后再按一下[，就可以得到“°”。
虽然看起来很像，但是这个（U+02DA）并不是度数那个符号（U+00B0）。同理这个也可以
在其他方言中使用－AltGr和[同时按，松开[，再按[就可以得到“¨”。


By pressing AltGr, Shift and [ at once, releasing them, and then pressing a, a
Scandinavian 'å' is produced. Similarly, when I press AltGr, Shift and [ at
once, release <e>only</e> the [, and then press it again, '˚' is produced.
Although it looks like one, this (U+02DA) is not the same as a degree symbol
(U+00B0). This works for other accents produced by dead keys — AltGr and [,
releasing only the [, then pressing it again makes '¨'.
</p>

<p>
AltGr可以单独和字母键组合。比如，AltGr和m，可以组合出一个希腊小写字母mu：'µ'。
AltGr和s组合出一个ß。很多欧洲用户会期待（因为键盘上这么标明的）AltGr和4能组合
出一个欧元符号€。

AltGr can be used with alphabetical keys alone. For example, AltGr and m, a
Greek lower-case letter mu is produced: 'µ'. AltGr and s produce a
scharfes s or esszet: 'ß'. As many Europeanusers would expect (because
it is marked on their keyboard), AltGr and 4 (or E depending on the keyboard
layout) produces a Euro sign, '€'.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>资源</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode">Wikipedia上的Unicode页</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8">Wikipedia上的UTF-8页</uri>
  </li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.unicode.org">Unicode.org</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.utf-8.com">UTF-8.com</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3629.txt">RFC 3629</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2277.txt">RFC 2277</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/200x/2003/04/26/UTF">字符 vs. 字节</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
